A Guide to the Scrapbooks of Harry F. Byrd, Sr., ca. 1897-1927
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Scrapbooks of Harry F. Byrd, Sr. ca. 1897-1927
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
9700-e
This collection consists of 12 volumes.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access to the Harry F. Byrd, Sr., Papers is controlled by the Honorable Harry F. Byrd, Jr. An applicant for access who is not associated with the University of Virginia must furnish to the Director of Special Collections a brief description of his academic or other qualifications, a summary of his research project, and a description of any projected publication that might make use of material from, or material derived from, the Harry F. Byrd, Sr., Papers. The Director of Special Collections will contact Senator Byrd and will notify the applicant of the Senator's decision.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the University of Virginia Library by Rebecca Ebert of Handley Library, Winchester, Virginia, on November 15, 1999.
Scope and Content Information
This addition to the papers of Harry F. Byrd, Sr. consists of twelve scrapbooks, ca. 1897-1927, containing news clippings, programs, correspondence, pamphlets and miscellany relating to his early career and the Byrd family.
Specific topics include the appointment of Judge William F. Rhea to the State Corporation Commission, the murder trial of Robert O. Garrett, Tom Byrd's World War I service, and Richard E. Byrd's souvenirs from the American Commission to Negotiate Peace.
Other topics consist of the Virginia Democratic Paraty, the Federal Fuel Administration, the Southern Bell Telephone and Telegraph Company, the 1919 Virginia Senate race, the Valley Turnpike Company, the Virginia State Highway Dept., taxation in Virginia, the 1925 gubernatorial race, Byrd's term as governor of Virginia, and Al Smith the 1928 Democratic presidential nomination.
Arrangement
These items are arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Sr., 1897-1925
  This collection contains letters, news clippings, telegrams, certificates, and memorabilia, concerning the three brothers, Harry F. Byrd, Sr., Richard E. Byrd, and Thomas Bolling Byrd, and their father, Richard Evelyn Byrd as Speaker of the House of Delegates, and as a possible gubernatorial candidate in 1915. Other topics include joint resolution regarding the death of Henry Delaware Flood, clippings about the invention of a sextant by R.E. Byrd, the controversy over the possible appointment of Judge William F. Rhea to the Corporation Commission, the history of Richmond, and letters & many clippings about the murder trial of Clerk of the Court Robert O. Garrett who shot the Rev. E.L. Pierce in Cumberland County, prosecuted by R.E. Byrd. The collection also includes personal letters of Tom Byrd to his parents and his involvement with the Company G, 120th Infantry during World War I, passport of R.E. Byrd and other memorabilia of his trip to France as part of the American Commission to Negotiate Peace. Other correspondents include Gardner L. Boothe, H.D. Flood, Carter Glass, T.W. Harrison, C. Bascom Slemp, Claude A. Swanson, and St. George Tucker, in black covers.
- Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Sr., 1905-1919
  This collection contains letters and news clippings concerning Byrd's service with and resignation from the Federal Fuel Administration, Byrd's work as manager of the Southern Bell Telephone and Telegraph Company, his decision to run again for the Virginia Senate in 1919, and the war service of Richard E. Byrd and Thomas Bolling Byrd. Correspondents include Henry C. Stuart, R. Gray Williams (giving his suggestions for inprovements to The Evening Journal), Woodrow Wilson, and other politicians and business leaders, in black marbled covers
- Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Sr., 1908
  This collection contains news clippings regarding Byrd's election as President of the Valley Turnpike Company, in maroon marbled covers.
- Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Sr., 1908-1916, 1918
  This collection contains letters and telegrams from many different businessmen throughout the state concerning Byrd's resignation as the Federal Fuel Administrator for Virginia in order to enter the Army. There are two letters from Woodrow Wilson, several from Governor Henry C. Stuart, and one from his brother, Richard. This collection includes some news clippings, in black marbled covers
- Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Sr., 1921-1925
  This collection contains letters, news clippings and other documents, from W.L. Andrews, Dr. Kate Waller Barrett, S.O. Bland, John Stewart Bryan, E.R. Combs, Thomas J. Downing, Carter Glass, T.W. Harrison, John Garland Pollard, John O. Rodes, Jr., Henry C. Stuart, Claude A. Swanson, E. Lee Trinkle, John W. Williams, Woodrow Wilson, Clifton A. Woodrum, and many other politicians and business leaders. Some items discuss the reorganization of the Virginia State Highway Department and Byrd's selection as the Chairman of the Virginia Democratic Committee. Also included is a copy of the plan of T.W. Harrison regarding state roads submitted to Harry F. Byrd, Sr. and various methods of taxation in other states and those proposed for Virginia, in black covers.
- Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Sr., 1925
  This collection contains news clippings about Byrd's gubernatorial campaign of 1925 and correspondence supporting his bid for the governorship, in black covers.
- Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Sr., 1925-1926
  This collection contains news clippings in brown covers.
- Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Sr., February- August, 1926
  This collection contains news clippings concerning the beginning of Byrd's gubernatorial administration in brown covers.
- Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Sr., July- December, 1926
  This collection contains news clippings concerning Byrd's gubernatorial administration in brown covers.
- Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Sr., December 1926- March 1927
  This collection contains news clippings concerning Byrd's gubernatorial administration, in brown covers.
- Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Sr., March- April, 1927
  This collection contains news clippings concerning Byrd's gubernatorial administration and the candidacy of Governor Alfred E. Smith of New York for the Democratic presidential nomination, in brown covers.
- Scrapbook of Harry F. Byrd, Sr., August- September, 1927